<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Imperial Edict of February 13, 1901 - Boxer Protocol Related Document</title>
        <author>Qing Imperial Court</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Translation</resp>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Historical Archive</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Beijing, China</pubPlace>
        <date when="1901-02-13">February 13, 1901</date>
        <availability>
          <p>Public Domain</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>English translation of Imperial Edict issued by the Qing Dynasty following the Boxer Rebellion, related to the Boxer Protocol signed on September 7, 1901.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="LCSH">
          <term>Boxer Rebellion, China, 1899-1901</term>
          <term>China -- History -- 1861-1912</term>
          <term>Treaties</term>
          <term>Imperial edicts</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="edict">
        <head>IMPERIAL EDICT of the <date when="1901-02-13">13th of February, 1901</date></head>
        
        <div type="section" n="1">
          <p>Since the <date when="1900-05">5th moon (end of May)</date> the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName> have created trouble in the capital and have begun hostilities against friendly countries. <persName ref="#yi_kuang">Yi-K'ung</persName> and <persName ref="#li_hongzhang">Li Hung-chang</persName> are negotiating for peace at <placeName ref="#beijing">Peking</placeName> with Representatives of the Powers, and a whole preliminary arrangement has already been signed.</p>
          
          <p>(If) We consider the commencement of these events, (we find that they are due) to several stupid, mad, utterly ignorant, turbulent Princes and Ministers who have trampled the laws under foot. They had most absolute confidence in pernicious methods and have involved the Court. Not only did they refuse to obey Our orders to exterminate the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName>, but they have gone so far as to believe in them, and, stupidly, they began to attack (the Legations). So it was that this evil fire spread abroad, and circumstances did not permit of its being stopped, tens of millions of evil-doers having assembled under the elbow and the armpit (that is to say, at a most important point). Furthermore, the leaders forced generals and ignorant soldiers to attack the Legations, and so it befell that inconceivable evils persisted for several months.</p>
          
          <p>The tutelary deities of the Empire have been in danger, the Imperial tombs and the temples of the Ancestors have trembled, the country has been devastated, the inhabitants are plunged in misery. No words can express the dangers to which We and H. M. the <persName ref="#cixi">Empress Dowager</persName> have been exposed. Our heart and our head are still in pain; our tears and our resentment are confounded. It is to you, Princes and Ministers, who, by believing in evil words and allowing evil-doers free hand, have put in danger in Heaven our Ancestors and our gods, and who here below have caused the people to endure these calamities. Do you ask what is the chastisement you deserve?</p>
        </div>
        
        <div type="section" n="2">
          <head>Punishments Decreed</head>
          
          <p>We have already issued two decrees. But, considering that such light punishments for such grievous faults could not be sufficient to make you expiate your crimes, We must impose upon you new and more severe punishments according to your degree of guilt.</p>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="1">
            <p><persName ref="#tsai_hsun">Tsai-hsün, Prince Chuang</persName>, already degraded, allowed the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName> to attack the Legations. He, on his own authority, published proclamations contrary to the treaties; he lightly believed the statements of evil-doers; he unlawfully caused to be decapitated a great number of persons; he has shown himself, of a truth, vulgar and stupid. We invite him, as a favor, to commit suicide. We direct <persName ref="#ko_pao_hua">Ko-pao-hua</persName>, acting president of the Court of Censors, to go and see (that the suicide has taken place).</p>
          </div>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="2">
            <p><persName ref="#tsai_i">Tsai-i, Prince Tuan</persName>, already degraded, led away with him several Princes and Peilo (Princes of the 3d class). He lightly gave heed to the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName> and foolishly advised fighting. So all these troubles broke out; his faults, of a truth, can not be ignored. <persName ref="#tsai_lan">Tsai-lan, Duke Fu-Kuo</persName>, reduced in rank, in concert with <persName ref="#tsai_hsun">Tsai-Hsün</persName>, foolishly published proclamations contrary to the treaties. He should also be punished for his faults. We deprive them of their nobiliary titles, but, considering that they belong to our family, We order, by special act of grace, that they be sent to <placeName ref="#xinjiang">Hsin-chiang (Ili)</placeName> where they shall be condemned to prison for life. Deputies will first be sent to watch them.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="3">
            <p><persName ref="#yu_xian">Yü-hsien</persName>, degraded governor, foolishly believed, when formerly discharging the duties of governor in <placeName ref="#shandong">Shantung</placeName>, in the sorcery of the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName>. Arriving in <placeName ref="#beijing">Peking</placeName>, he extolled them so highly that several Princes and Ministers fell under his evil influence. Being governor of <placeName ref="#shanxi">Shansi</placeName>, he massacred a great number of missionaries and Christians. He is worse than an imbecile, than a madman, than a murderer; he is the chief culprit and the author of all these calamities. He has already been sent to <placeName ref="#xinjiang">Hsin-chiang</placeName>, and, believing that he has arrived in <placeName ref="#gansu">Kan-su</placeName>, We order that, on the receipt of the order which We send, he shall at once be beheaded. We direct the Provincial Judge <persName ref="#ho_fu_kun">Ho Fu-kun</persName> to see that the penalty is carried out.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="4">
            <p><persName ref="#kang_yi">Kang-yi</persName>, Assistant Grand Secretary of State, President of the Board of Works, having lent his aid to the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName>, serious disturbances broke out. He aided in publishing proclamations contrary to the treaties. A severe punishment was to have been inflicted on him at first, but he has died of disease. We order that the honors which he previously held shall be withdrawn from him and that he be at once degraded.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="5">
            <p><persName ref="#dong_fuxiang">Tung Fu-hsiang</persName>, general in <placeName ref="#gansu">Kan-su</placeName>, degraded but retained in office, entered (<placeName ref="#beijing">Peking</placeName>) to defend (the city) with the troops under his orders; he was unable to maintain strict discipline. Ignorant, furthermore, of international questions, he followed his ideas and acted in an imprudent manner. Although the attacks on the Legations were ordered by the above degraded Princes, it is nevertheless difficult to absolve him of all faults. We intended in the first instance to have punished him severely, but, considering the signal services he has rendered in <placeName ref="#gansu">Kan-su</placeName> and the sympathy felt for him by Mussulmans and Chinese, as an act of extraordinary grace We order that he shall be immediately degraded.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="6">
            <p><persName ref="#ying_nien">Ying-nien</persName>, President of the Court of Censors, reduced in rank and displaced, opposed <persName ref="#tsai_hsun">Tsai-Hün</persName> in publishing on his own authority proclamations contrary to the treaties. We may make due allowance for this circumstance, but as he was not able to overcome (this resistance) by force, it is, after all, difficult to absolve him. We order, as a mark of great benevolence, that he be degraded. We condemn him to death, and he shall wait in prison for his case to be passed on.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="7">
            <p><persName ref="#zhao_shujiao">Chao Shu-chiao</persName>, President of the Board of Punishments, degraded and retained in office, had never shown till then any unfriendly feeling in relations with the Foreign Powers. Having made a report on the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName>, he said nothing in their favor, but through his negligence faults were made. We order, as a special act of grace, that he be degraded. We condemn him to death, and he will await in prison judgment on his case.</p>
            
            <p>We command that <persName ref="#ying_nien">Ying-nien</persName> and <persName ref="#zhao_shujiao">Chao Shu-chiao</persName> be in the first place confined in the prison of the capital of <placeName ref="#shaanxi">Shensi</placeName>.</p>
          </div>
          
          <div type="punishment" n="8">
            <p><persName ref="#xu_tong">Hsu Tung</persName>, Grand Secretary of State, and <persName ref="#li_bingheng">Li Ping-heng</persName>, former Governor-General of <placeName ref="#sichuan">Sze-chuan</placeName>, reduced in rank and displaced, died for their country, but everyone knows their faults. We order that they be degraded, and We deprive them of the posthumous honors which We had conferred on them.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        
        <div type="conclusion">
          <p>After the promulgation of this decree all our friendly nations should recognize that the events caused by the <orgName ref="#boxers">Boxers</orgName> are in truth only attributable to the principal authors of trouble and in no wise to the wishes of the Court.</p>
          
          <p>Since We, the Emperor, not without reason do punish several of the principal authors of disorder, the mandarins and the people of the Empire will understand at once that the consequences of such affairs are of the most grave.</p>
          
          <p>Respect this!</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    
    <back>
      <listPerson>
        <person xml:id="yi_kuang">
          <persName>Yi-K'ung (Prince Qing)</persName>
          <note>Senior Qing official involved in peace negotiations</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="li_hongzhang">
          <persName>Li Hung-chang</persName>
          <note>Senior Qing official and diplomat</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="cixi">
          <persName>Empress Dowager Cixi</persName>
          <note>De facto ruler of Qing China during this period</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="tsai_hsun">
          <persName>Tsai-hsün, Prince Chuang</persName>
          <note>Qing prince punished for supporting Boxers</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="tsai_i">
          <persName>Tsai-i, Prince Tuan</persName>
          <note>Qing prince, major supporter of Boxers</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="tsai_lan">
          <persName>Tsai-lan, Duke Fu-Kuo</persName>
          <note>Qing noble punished for anti-foreign actions</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="yu_xian">
          <persName>Yü-hsien</persName>
          <note>Governor of Shanxi, executed for massacring missionaries</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="kang_yi">
          <persName>Kang-yi</persName>
          <note>Assistant Grand Secretary, supporter of Boxers</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="dong_fuxiang">
          <persName>Tung Fu-hsiang</persName>
          <note>General from Gansu</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="ying_nien">
          <persName>Ying-nien</persName>
          <note>President of the Court of Censors</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="zhao_shujiao">
          <persName>Chao Shu-chiao</persName>
          <note>President of the Board of Punishments</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="xu_tong">
          <persName>Hsu Tung</persName>
          <note>Grand Secretary of State</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="li_bingheng">
          <persName>Li Ping-heng</persName>
          <note>Former Governor-General of Sichuan</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="ko_pao_hua">
          <persName>Ko-pao-hua</persName>
          <note>Acting president of the Court of Censors</note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="ho_fu_kun">
          <persName>Ho Fu-kun</persName>
          <note>Provincial Judge</note>
        </person>
      </listPerson>
      
      <listPlace>
        <place xml:id="beijing">
          <placeName>Peking (Beijing)</placeName>
          <location>
            <geo>39.9042 116.4074</geo>
          </location>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="xinjiang">
          <placeName>Hsin-chiang (Xinjiang/Ili)</placeName>
          <note>Remote western region used for exile</note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="shandong">
          <placeName>Shantung (Shandong)</placeName>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="shanxi">
          <placeName>Shansi (Shanxi)</placeName>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="gansu">
          <placeName>Kan-su (Gansu)</placeName>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="shaanxi">
          <placeName>Shensi (Shaanxi)</placeName>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="sichuan">
          <placeName>Sze-chuan (Sichuan)</placeName>
        </place>
      </listPlace>
      
      <listOrg>
        <org xml:id="boxers">
          <orgName>Boxers (Yihetuan)</orgName>
          <note>Anti-foreign, anti-Christian movement in China, 1899-1901</note>
        </org>
      </listOrg>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>